Chapter 18 Merry days were these at Thornfield Hall, and busy days, too.
How different from the first three months of stillness,
monotony, and solitude I had passed beneath its roof.
All sad feelings seemed now driven from the house, or gloomy associations forgotten.
There was life everywhere, movement all day long.
You could not now traverse the gallery, once so hushed, nor enter the front
chambers, once so tenantless, without
encountering a smart lady's made or a dandy valet.
The kitchen, the butler's pantry, the servants hall, the entrance hall,
were equally alive, and the saloons were only left void and still, when the blue
sky and halcyon sunshine of the genial spring
weather called their occupants out into the grounds.
Even when that weather was broken, and continuous rain set in for some days,
no damp seemed cast over enjoyment.
Indoor amusements only became more lively and varied in consequence of the stop put
to outdoor gaiety.
I wondered what they were going to do the first
evening a change of entertainment was proposed.
They spoke of playing charades, but in my ignorance, I did not understand the term.
The servants were called in, the dining room tables wheeled away, the lights
otherwise disposed, the chairs placed in a semicircle opposite the arch.
While Mr. Rochester and the other gentlemen directed these alterations,
the ladies were running up and downstairs ringing for their maids.
Mrs. Fairfax was summoned to give information respecting the resources of
the house in shores, dresses, draperies of any kind.
And certain wardrobes of the third story were ransacked, and their contents in the
shape of brocaded and hooped petticoats sat in sacks, black modes, lace lepets, etc.
were brought down in armfuls by the abigales.
Then a selection was made, and such things as were chosen
were carried to the boudoir within the drawing room.
Meantime, Mr. Rochester had again summoned the ladies around him and was selecting
certain of their number to be of his party.
Miss Ingram is mine, of course, said he.
Afterwards, he named the two Mrs. Eshton and Mrs. Dent.
He looked at me.
I happened to be near him as I had been fastening the clasp of Mrs.
Dent's bracelet, which had got loose.
Will you play?
He asked.
I shook my head.
He did not insist, which I rather feared he would have done.
He allowed me to return quietly to my usual seat.
He and his aides now withdrew behind the curtain.
The other party, which was headed by Colonel
Dent, sat down on the crescent of chairs.
One of the gentlemen, Mr. Eshton, observing me, seemed to propose that I
should be asked to join them, but Lady Ingram instantly negative to the notion.
No, I heard her say.
She looks too stupid for any game of the sort.
A long bell tinkled and the curtain drew up.
Within the arch, the bulky figure of Sir George Lynn, who Mr. Rochester had
likewise chosen, was seen enveloped in a white sheet.
Before him, on a table lay open a large book.
And at his side stood Amy Eshton, draped in
Mr. Rochester's cloak and holding a book in her hand.
Somebody unseen rang the bell merrily, then Adele, who had insisted on being one
of her guardians' party, bounded forward, scattering around
her the contents of a basket of flowers she carried on her arm.
Then appeared the magnificent figure of Miss Ingram, clad in white, a long veil on
her head, and a wreath of roses round her brow.
By her side walked Mr. Rochester, and together they drew near the table, they knelt.
While Mrs. Dent and Louisa Eshton, dressed also
in white, took up their stations behind them.
A ceremony followed in dumb show, in which it was
easy to recognise the pantomime of a marriage.
At its termination, Colonel Dent and his party consulted in whispers for two minutes.
Then, the Colonel called out, cried, Mr. Rochester bowed, and the curtain fell.
A considerable interval elapsed before it again rose.
Its second rising, displayed a more elaborately prepared scene than the last.
The drawing-room, as I have before observed,
was raised two steps above the dining -room.
And on the top of the upper step, placed a yard or two back within the room,
appeared a large marble basin, which I recognised as an ornament of the
conservatory, where it usually stood, surrounded by exotics and tenented by goldfish.
And once it must have been transported with
some trouble on account of its size and weight.
Seated on the carpet by the side of this basin was seen
Mr. Rochester, costume in shawls with a turban on his head.
His dark eyes and swarthy skin and pain in features suited the costume exactly.
He looked the very model of an eastern emir, an agent or a victim of the bowstring.
Presently advanced interview, Miss Ingram.
She too was a tired in oriental fashion.
A crimson scarf tied sash-like around the waist.
An embroidered hankerchief knotted about her temples.
Her beautifully moulded arms bare, one of them upraised in the act of
supporting a picture, poised gracefully on her head.
Both her cast of form and feature, her complexion and her general air,
suggested the idea of some israelitish princess of the patriarchal days.
And such was doubtless the character she intended to represent.
She approached the basin and bent over it as if to fill her picture.
She again lifted it to her head.
The personage on the well-brink now seemed to accost her.
To make some request, she hasted, let down
her picture on her hand and gave him to drink.
From the bosom of his robe, he then produced a casket,
opened it, and showed magnificent bracelets and earrings.
She acted astonishment and admiration.
Kneeling, he laid the treasure at her feet.
In credulity and delight were expressed by her looks and gestures.
The stranger fussed the bracelets on her arms and the rings in her ears.
It was a laser and Rebecca.
The camels only were wanting.
The divining party again laid their heads together.
Apparently, they could not agree about the word or syllable the scene illustrated.
Colonel Dent, their spokesman, demanded the tablo of the whole.
Whereupon the curtain again descended.
On its third rising, only a portion of the drawing-room was disclosed.
The rest being concealed by a screen, hung with some sort of dark and coarse drapery.
The marble basin was removed.
In its place stood a deal table and a kitchen chair.
These objects were visible by a very dim light proceeding from a horn lantern.
The wax candles being all extinguished.
Amidst this sordid scene, sat a man with his clenched
hands resting on his knees and his eyes bent on the ground.
I knew Mr. Rochester, though the begrimmed face, the disordered dress, his coat
hanging loose from one arm, as if it had been almost torn from his back in a scuffle.
The desperate and scowling countenance, the rough,
bristling hair might well have disguised him.
As he moved, a chain clanked to his wrists were attached fetters.
Bride well, exclaimed Colonel Dent, and the charade was solved.
A sufficient interval, having elapsed for the performers to
resume their ordinary costume, they re-entered the dining-room.
Mr. that of the three characters.
I liked you in the last best.
Oh, had you but lived a few years earlier?
What a gallant gentleman highwayman you would have made.
Is all the suit washed from my face, he asked, turning it towards her?
Alas, yes, the more's the pity.
Nothing could be more becoming to your complexion than that ruffian's rouge.
You would like a hero of the road then.
An English hero of the road would be the next best thing to an Italian bandit,
and that could only be surpassed by eleven teen pirate.
Well, whatever I am, remember you are my wife.
We were married an hour since, in the presence of all these witnesses.
She giggled, and her colour rose.
Now Dent continued Mr. Rochester.
It is your turn.
And as the other party withdrew, he and his band took the vacated seats.
Missing room placed herself at her leader's right hand, the other diviners
filled the chairs on each side of him and her.
I did not now watch the actors.
I no longer waited with interest for the curtain to rise.
My attention was absorbed by the spectators.
My eyes, air while fixed on the arch, were now
irresistibly attracted to the semicircle of chairs.
What charade Colonel Dent and his party played?
What word they chose?
How they acquitted themselves?
I no longer remember, but I still see the consultation which followed each scene.
I see Mr. Rochester turn to Missingroom, and Missingroom to him.
I see her incline her head towards him till the jetty
curls almost touch his shoulder and wave against his cheek.
I hear their mutual whisperings.
I recall their interchanged glances and something even of the feeling roused by
the spectacle returns in memory at this moment.
I have told you, reader, that I had learnt to love Mr. Rochester.
I could not unlove him now merely because I found that he had ceased to notice me,
because I might pass hours in his presence and he would never once turn his eyes in
my direction, because I saw all his attentions appropriated by a great lady,
who scorned to touch me with the hem of her robes as she passed, who, if ever her
dark and imperious eye fell on me by chance, would withdraw it instantly as
from an object too mean to merit observation.
I could not unlove him because I felt sure he would soon marry this very lady,
because I read daily in her a proud security in his intentions respecting her,
because I witnessed hourly in him a style of courtship, which, if careless and
choosing rather to be sought than to seek, was yet in its very carelessness
captivating and in its very pride irresistible.
There was nothing to call or banish love in these circumstances, though much to
create despair, much too you will think, reader, to engender jealousy.
If a woman, in my position, could presume to be jealous of a woman in Miss Ingrams,
but I was not jealous or very rarely, the nature of the pain I suffered could
not be explained by that word, Miss Ingram was a mark beneath jealousy,
she was too inferior to excite the feeling.
Pardon the seeming paradox, I mean what I say,
she was very showy, but she was not genuine.
She had a fine person, many brilliant attainments, but her mind was poor,
her heart barren by nature, nothing bloomed spontaneously on that soil,
no unforced natural fruit delighted by its freshness, she was not good, she was not
original, she used to repeat sounding phrases from books, she never offered,
nor had, an opinion of her own, she advocated a high tone of sentiment,
but she did not know the sensations of sympathy and pity, tenderness and truth
were not in her.
Too often she betrayed this, by the undue vent she gave to a spiteful antipathy she
had conceived against little Adele, pushing her away with some contomelius
epithet if she happened to approach her, sometimes ordering her from the room and
always treating her with coldness and acrimony.
Other eyes, besides mine, watched these manifestations
of character, watched them closely, keenly, shrewdly.
Yes, the future bridegroom, Mr. Rochester himself, exercised over his intended a
ceaseless surveillance, and it was from this sagacity, this guardedness of his,
this perfect clear consciousness of his fair ones defects, this obvious absence of
passion in his sentiments towards her, that my ever torturing pain arose.
I saw he was going to marry her, for family, perhaps political reasons,
because her rank in connections suited him.
I felt he had not given her his love, and that her
qualifications were ill -adapted to win from him that treasure.
This was the point, this was where the nerve was touched and teased, this was
where the fever was sustained and fed, she could not charm him.
If she had managed the victory at once, and he had yielded and sincerely laid his
heart at her feet, I should have covered my face, turned to the wall, and
figuratively, have died to them.
If Miss Ingram had been a good and noble woman, endowed with force, further
kindness sense, I should have had one vital struggle with two tigers,
jealousy and despair.
Then, my heart torn out and devoured, I should have admired her, acknowledged
her excellence, and been quiet for the rest of my days, and the more absolute her
superiority, the deeper would have been my
admiration, the more truly tranquil my quiescence.
But as matters really stood, to watch Miss Ingram's efforts at fascinating Mr.
Rochester, to witness their repeated failure, herself unconscious that they did fail.
Vainly fanciing that each shaft launched hit the mark, and infatuatedly pluming
herself on success, when her pride and self complacency repelled further and
further what she wished to allure, to witness this, was to be at once under
ceaseless excitation and ruthless restraint, because when she failed,
I saw how she might have succeeded, arrows that continually glanced off from
Mr. Rochester's breast and fell harmless at his feet.
Might, I knew, if shot by a sure hand, have quivered keen in his proud heart,
have called love into his stern eye and softness into his sardonic face.
Or better still, without weapons a silent conquest might have been won.
Why can she not influence him more, when she is privileged to draw so near to him?
I ask myself, surely she cannot truly like him, or not like him with true affection.
If she did, she need not coin her smile so lavishly, flash her glances so
unremittingly, manufacture air so elaborate, graces so multitudinous.
It seems to me that she might, by merely sitting quietly at his side,
saying little and looking less, get nigher his heart.
I have seen in his face a far different expression from that which hardens it now,
while she is so vivaciously accosting him.
But then it came of itself.
It was not elicited by meritricious arts and calculated maneuvers, and one had but
to accept it, to answer what he asked without pretension, to address him when
needful without grimace, and it increased and grew kinder and more genial,
and warmed one like a fostering sunbeam.
How will she manage to please him when they are married?
I do not think she will manage it, and yet it might be managed, and his wife
might, I verily believe, be the very happiest woman, the sun shines on.
I have not yet said anything condemnatory of Mr. Rochester's
project of marrying for interest and connections.
It surprised me when I first discovered that such was his intention.
I had thought him a man unlikely to be influenced by motives so commonplace in
his choice of a wife, but the longer I considered the position, education, etc.
, of the parties, the less I felt justified in judging and blaming,
either him or Miss Ingram for acting in conformity to ideas and principles
instilled into them, doubtless from their childhood.
All their class held these principles.
I suppose then they had reasons for holding them such as I could not fathom.
It seemed to me that, where I a gentleman like him, I would take to my bosom only
such a wife as I could love, but the very obviousness of the advantages to the
husband's own happiness offered by this plan convinced me that there must be
arguments against its general adoption of which I was quite ignorant, otherwise I
felt sure all the world would act as I wished to act.
But in other points, as well as this, I was growing very lenient to my master.
I was forgetting all his faults, for which I had once kept a sharp lookout.
It had formerly been my endeavour to study all sides of his character, to take the
bad with the good, and from the just weighing of both, to form an equitable judgment.
Now I saw no bad.
The sarcasm that had repelled, the harshness that had startled me once,
were only like keen condiments in a choice dish.
Their presence was pungent, but their absence would be felt as comparatively
insipid, and as for the vague something, was it a sinister or a sorrowful,
a designing or a desponding expression?
That opened upon a careful observer, now and then, in his eye, and closed again
before one could fathom the strange depth partially disclosed.
That's something which used to make me fear and shrink, as if I had been
wandering amongst volcanic-looking hills, and had suddenly felt the ground quiver
and seen it gap.
That's something I, at intervals, beheld still, and with throbbing heart,
but not with palsyed nerves.
Instead of wishing to shun, I longed only to dare, to divine it, and I thought Miss
Ingram happy, because one day she might look into the abyss at her leisure,
explore its secrets, and analyse their nature.
Meantime, while I thought only of my master and his future bride, saw only
them, heard only their discourse, and considered only their movements of
importance, the rest of the party were occupied
with their own separate interests and pleasures.
The ladies Lin and Ingram continued to consort in solemn conferences,
where they nodded their two turbans at each other, and held up their forehands in
confronting gestures of surprise or mystery or horror, according to the theme
on which their gossip ran, like a pair of magnified puppets, mild Mrs. Dent talked
with good-natured Mrs. Eshton, and the two
sometimes bestowed a courteous word or smile on me.
So George Lin, Colonel Dent, and Mr. Eshton discussed
politics, or county affairs, or justice business.
Lord Ingram flirted with Amy Eshton, Luisa played and sang two and with one of
the messes Lin, and Mary Ingram listened
languidly to the gallant speeches of the other.
Sometimes all, as with one consent, suspended their
bi-play to observe and listen to the principal actors.
Four, after all, Mr. Rochester and, because closely connected with him,
Miss Ingram were the life and soul of the party.
If he was absent from the room an hour, a perceptible dullness seemed to steal
over the spirits of his guests, and his re-entrance was sure to give a
fresh impulse to the vivacity of conversation.
The want of his animating influence appeared to be peculiarly felt one day
that he had been summoned to Mill Court on
business, and was not likely to return till late.
The afternoon was wet.
A walk the party had proposed to take to see a gypsy camp, lately pitched on a
common beyond hay, was consequently deferred.
Some of the gentlemen were gone to the stables.
The younger ones, together with the younger ladies,
were playing billiards in the billiard room.
The Dowagers, Ingram and Lin sought solace in a quiet game at cards.
Blanch Ingram, after having repelled by super-cilious taciturnity, some efforts of
Mrs. Dent and Mrs. Eshton to draw her into conversation, had first murmured over some
sentimental tunes and heirs on the piano, and then, having fetched a novel from the
library, had flung herself in haughty listlessness on a sofa, and prepared to
beguile by the spell of fiction, the tedious hours of absence.
The room in the house was silent.
Only now and then, the merriment of the billiard players was heard from above.
It was verging on dusk, and the clock had already given warning of the hour to dress
for dinner, when Little Adele, who knelt by me in the drawing-room window
-seat, suddenly exclaimed, Voila, Monsieur Roche-Stere, Girevion.
I turned, and Miss Ingram darted forwards from her sofa, the others too,
looked up from their several occupations, for at the same time a crunching of wheels
and a splashing tramp of horse hooves became audible on the wet gravel,
a post-chase was approaching.
What can possess him to come home in that style?
said Miss Ingram.
He rode Miss Roer, the black horse, did he
not, when he went out, and Pyle was with him.
What has he done with the animals?
As she said this, she approached her tall person and ample garment so near the
window that I was obliged to bend back almost to the breaking of my spine.
In her eagerness she did not observe me at first, but when
she did, she curled her lip and moved to another casement.
The post-chase stopped, the driver rang the doorbell, and a gentleman alighted a
tired in traveling garb, but it was not Mr. Rochester.
It was a tall, fashionable looking man, a stranger.
How provoking, exclaimed Miss Ingram, you tire some monkey, a post-refizing
Adele, who perched you up in the window to give false intelligence.
And she cast on me an angry glance as if I were in fault.
Some parliing was audible in the hall, and soon the newcomer entered.
He bowed to Lady Ingram, as deeming her the eldest lady present.
It appears I come at an inopportune-time madam, said he, when my friend Mr.
Rochester is from home.
But I arrive from a very long journey, and I think I may presume so far on old
and intimate acquaintance, and as to install myself here till he returns.
His manner was polite.
His accent, in speaking, struck me as being somewhat unusual,
not precisely foreign, but still not altogether English.
His age might be about Mr. Rochester's.
Between 30 and 40, his complexion was singularly salo, otherwise
he was a fine -looking man, at first sight, especially.
On closer examination, you detected something in his face that displeased,
or rather that failed to please.
His features were regular but too relaxed.
His eye was large and well-cut, but the life looking
out of it was a tame vacant life, at least so I thought.
The sound of the dressing-bell dispersed the party,
it was not till after dinner that I saw him again.
He then seemed quite at his ease, but I liked his physiognomy even less than before.
It struck me as being at the same time unsettled and inanimate.
His eye wandered, and had no meaning in its wandering.
This gave him an odd look, such as I never remembered to have seen.
For a handsome and not an unamiable looking man, he repelled me exceedingly.
There was no power in that smooth skinned face of a full oval shape.
No firmness in that aquiline nose and small cherry mouth.
There was no thought on the low even forehead, no command in that blank brown eye.
As I sat in my usual nook and looked at him with the light
of the gerandales on the mantelpiece beaming full over him.
For he occupied an armchair, drawn close to the fire,
and kept shrinking still nearer, as if he was cold.
I compared him with Mr. Rochester.
I think, with deference be it spoken, the contrast could not be much greater
between a leak, gander, and a fierce falcon between a meek
sheep and the rough -coated keen-eyed dog, its guardian.
He had spoken of Mr. Rochester as an old friend.
A curious friendship theirs must have been.
A pointed illustration, indeed, of the old adage that extremes meet.
Two or three of the conversation across the room.
At first I could not make much sense of what I heard.
For the discourse of Luisa Eshton and Mary Ingram, who sat near it to me,
confused the fragmentary sentences that reached me at
intervals, these last were discussing the stranger.
They both called him a beautiful man.
Luisa said he was a love of a creature, and she adored him, and Mary instanced his
pretty little mouth and nice nose as her ideal of the charming.
And what a sweet, tempered forehead he has, cried Luisa.
So smooth, none of those frowning irregularities I dislike so much,
and such a placid eye and smile.
And then, to my great relief, Mr. Henry Lin summoned them to the other side of the
room to settle some point about the deferred excursion to hey common.
I was now able to concentrate my attention on the group by the fire, and I presently
gathered that the newcomer was called Mr. Mason.
Then I learned that he was but just arrived in England and that he came from
some hot country, which was the reason, doubtless, his face was so salo,
and that he sat so near the hearth and wore a shirt out in the house.
Presently, the words Jamaica, Kingston, Spanish Town indicated the West Indies as
his residence, and it was with no little surprise I gathered air long, that he had
their first scene and become acquainted with Mr. Rochester.
He spoke of his friends dislike of the burning heats, the hurricanes,
and rainy seasons of that region.
I knew Mr. Rochester had been a traveler, Mrs. Fairfax had said so, but I thought
the continent of Europe had bounded his wanderings.
Till now, I had never heard a hint given a visit to more distant shores.
I was pondering these things, when an incident and a somewhat unexpected one
broke the thread of my musings.
Mr. Mason, shivering as someone chance to open the door, asked for more coal to be
put on the fire, which had burnt out its flame,
though its mass of cinder still shone hot and red.
The footmen who brought the coal in going out, stopped near Mr. Eston's chair and
said something to him in a low voice of which I heard only the words, old woman,
quite troublesome.
Tell her she shall be put in the stocks if she does not take herself off,
replied the magistrate.
No, stop interrupted Colonel Dent.
Don't send her away, Eston.
We might turn the thing to account, better consult the ladies.
And speaking aloud, he continued.
Ladies, you talked of going to hey common to visit the gypsy camp.
Sam here says that one of the old mother -bunches is in the servants' hall at this
moment, and insists upon being brought in
before the quality to tell them their fortunes.
Would you like to see her?
Surely Colonel cried Lady Ingram, you would not encourage such a low
imposter, dismiss her by all means at once.
But I cannot persuade her to go away my lady,
said the footmen, nor can any of the servants.
Mrs. Fairfax is with her just now, in treating her to be gone.
But she has taken a chair in the chimney corner, and says nothing shall stir her
from it till she gets leave to come in here.
What does she want?
asked Mrs. Eston.
To tell the gentry their fortunes, she says,
ma'am, and she swears she must and will do it.
What is she like?
inquired the Mrs. Eston in a breath, a shockingly ugly old creature miss,
almost as black as a croc.
Why, she's a real sorceress, cried Frederick Lynn.
Let us have her in, of course.
To be sure, rejoined his brother, it would be a
thousand pities to throw away such a chance of fun.
My dear boys, what are you thinking about?
Exclaimed Mrs. Lynn.
I cannot possibly countenance any such inconsistent
proceeding, chimed in the Dowager Ingram.
Indeed, ma'am, but you can, and will, pronounce the haughty voice of Blanche,
as she turned round on the piano stool, where till now she had sat silent,
apparently examining sundry sheets of music.
I have a curiosity to hear my fortune told, therefore Sam, order the bell-dame forward.
My darling Blanche, recollect, I do, I recollect all you can suggest,
and I must have my will, quick Sam.
Yes, yes, yes, cried all the juveniles, both ladies and gentlemen, let her come,
it will be excellent sport.
The footman still lingered.
She looked such a rough one, said he.
Go, a jack-ulated Miss Ingram, and the man went.
Excitement instantly seized the whole party, a running
fire of railery and jests was proceeding when Sam returned.
She won't come now, said he.
She says, it's not her mission to appear before the vulgar herd, them's her words.
I must show her into a room by herself, and then those who wish to consult her
must go to her one by one.
You see now my queenly Blanche began lady Ingram, she encroaches, be advised my
angel girl, and show her into the library of course, cut in the angel girl.
It is not my mission to listen to her before the vulgar herd, either.
I mean to have her all to myself, is there a fire in the library?
Yes, ma'am, but she looks such a tinkler.
Seized that chatter blockhead and do my bidding.
Again, Sam vanished, and mystery, animation, expectation rose to full flow once more.
She's ready now, said the footman.
As he reappeared, she wishes to know who will be her first visitor.
I think I had better just look in upon her
before any of the lady's go, said Colonel Dent.
Tell her, Sam, a gentleman is coming.
Sam went and returned.
She says, sir, that she'll have no gentleman, they need not trouble
themselves to come near her, nor he added, with difficulty suppressing a titter.
Any ladies, either, accept the young and single.
By Jov, she has taste, exclaimed Henry Lynn.
Miss Ingram rose solemnly, I go first, she said, in a tone which might have
befitted the leader of a fallon hope, mounting a breach in the van of his men.
Oh, my best, oh, my dearest, pause, reflect, was her mama's cry, but she swept
past her in stately silence, passed through the door which
Colonel Dent held open, and we heard her enter the library.
A comparative silence ensued.
Lady Ingram thought it, La Cass to ring her hands, which she did accordingly.
Miss Mary declared she felt, for her part, she never dared venture.
Amy and Luisa Eston titted under their breath and looked a little frightened.
The minutes passed very slowly, 15 were counted before the library door again opened.
Miss Ingram returned to us through the arch,
would she laugh, would she take it as a joke?
All eyes met her with a glance of eager curiosity, and
she met all eyes with one of her buff and coldness.
She looked neither flurried nor Mary.
She walked stiffly to her seat and took it in silence.
Well-blanch said Lord Ingram.
What did she say, sister?
Asked Mary.
What did you think?
How do you feel?
Is she a real fortune teller?
Demanded the Mrs. Eston.
Now, now, good people.
Returned Miss Ingram.
Don't press upon me.
Really, your organs of wonder and credulity are easily excited.
You seem, by the importance of you all.
My good Mama included.
Ascribed to this matter, absolutely to believe we have a genuine witch in the
house, who is in close alliance with the old gentleman.
I have seen a gypsy vagabond.
She has practised in hackneyed fashion the science of
palmistry and told me what such people usually tell.
My whim is gratified.
And now I think Mr. Eston will do well to put the hag in the stocks tomorrow morning
as he threatened.
Miss Ingram took a book, lent back in her
chair, and so declined further conversation.
I watched her for nearly half an hour.
During all that time she never turned a page, and her face grew momently darker,
more dissatisfied, and more sourly expressive of disappointment.
She had obviously not heard anything to her advantage.
And it seemed to me, from her prolonged fit of gloom and taciturnity, that she
herself, notwithstanding her professed indifference, attached
undue importance to whatever revelations had been made her.
Meantime, Mary Ingram, Amy and Louisa Eston declared they dared not go alone.
And yet they all wished to go.
A negotiation was open through the medium of the ambassador, Sam.
And after much pacing, two-and-fro, till, I think, the
said Sam's calves must have ached with the exercise.
Permission was at last, with great difficulty, extorted from the rigorous
sibil, for the three to wait upon her in a body.
Their visit was not so still as Miss Ingram's had been.
We heard hysterical giggling and little shrieks proceeding from the library,
and at the end of about twenty minutes, they burst the door open and came running
across the hall as if they were half -scared out of their wits.
I am sure she is something not right.
They cried one and all.
She told us such things.
She knows all about us.
And they sank breathless into the various seats the gentleman hastened to bring them.
Pressed for further explanation, they declared she had told them of things
they had said and done when they were mere children.
Described books and ornaments they had in their budwars at home.
Keepsakes that different relations had presented to them.
They affirmed that she had even divined their thoughts, and had whispered in the
ear of each, the name of the person she liked best in the world, and informed them
of what they most wished for.
Hear the gentleman interposed with earnest petitions to be further enlightened on
these two last named points, but they got only blushes, ejaculations, tremors,
and titters, in return for their opportunity.
The matrons mean time offered vinaigrettes and wielded fans, and again and again
reiterated the expression of their concern that their warning had not been taken in
time, and the elder gentleman laughed and the younger
urged their services on the agitated fair ones.
In the midst of the tumult, and while my eyes and ears were fully engaged in the
scene before me, I heard a hem close at my elbow.
I turned and saw Sam.
If you please miss, the gypsy declares that there is another young single lady in
the room, who has not been to her yet, and she
swears she will not go till she has seen all.
I thought it must be you.
There is no one else for it.
What shall I tell her?
Oh, I will go by all means, I answered, and I was glad of the unexpected
opportunity to gratify my much-excited curiosity.
I slipped out of the room, unobserved by any eye, for the company were gathered in
one mass about the trembling trio just returned,
and I closed the door quietly behind me.
If you like miss, said Sam, I'll wait in the hall for
you, and if she frightens you, just call and I'll come in.
No, Sam, return to the kitchen, I am not in the least afraid.
Nor was I, but I was a good deal interested and excited.